Today, let's start from the beginning.
今天我们先从第一点开始看。
Even if *interest rates* fall,
就算*利率*下降，
this is why home prices don't rise right away.
房价也不会立刻上涨，原因就在这里。
In the past, the formula was simple.
以前的逻辑很简单。
When rates went down,
利率一降，
borrowing became less burdensome.
贷款负担就减轻了。
Then more money flowed into the market,
这样一来，资金就会释放出来，
and buyers stepped in.
买盘也会跟上。
So home prices,
所以房价也会，
responded almost immediately.
马上作出反应。
But that's not the case now.
但现在不一样了。
This formula,
这套公式，
doesn't work *automatically* like it used to.
已经不像以前那样*一定*奏效了。
Even Seoul's apartment market,
尤其是首尔公寓市场，
doesn't move right away.
也不会立刻动起来。
Why is that?
为什么会这样呢？
Because real estate now,
因为现在的房地产，
doesn't move on interest rates alone anymore.
已经不是只靠利率这一个因素来驱动了。
In today's market,
现在的市场，
you have to look at people's *sentiment*.
还得看人们的*心理*。
You also have to look at income,
要看收入情况，
and the economic outlook too.
也要看经济前景。
If the future feels uncertain,
如果对未来感到不安，
even a small rate cut won't get people moving.
就算利率稍微降一点，也不会行动。
The backdrop makes it even clearer.
看背景就更清楚了。
In the past,
过去，
as soon as loans became easier to get, people bought.
只要贷款变容易，大家就马上买房。
Now it's different.
现在不一样了。
Across the Korean economy,
对整个韩国经济来说，
uncertainty is high.
不确定性很大。
There are concerns about slower growth,
有经济放缓的担忧，
and household debt is still a heavy burden.
家庭负债压力也很大。
Real income feels stuck.
实际收入增长也很乏力。
In this kind of environment,
在这种情况下，
even if rates come down a little,
就算利息稍微低一点，
it's hard to say,
也很难立刻下定决心买房。
now is the time to buy a home.
核心归根结底，
The key, in the end,
还是*购房意愿*。
is *buyer sentiment*.
房价不是只看数字就会上涨的。
Home prices don't rise just because of the numbers.
人们得觉得现在可以买了，
People have to feel like,
市场才会动起来。
now is a good time to buy.
现在首尔公寓市场也是，
Even in Seoul's apartment market right now,
部分热门区域还能撑住。
some high-demand areas are holding up.
但从整体来看，
But overall,
市场信心还是偏弱。
conviction is weak.
接下来还会不会涨，
Will prices go higher from here?
大家其实也拿不准。
People just aren't sure.
经济状况会不会好转，
Will the economy hold up?
这一点也没有把握。
They're not confident about that either.
自己的收入能不能撑住，
Will my income hold up?
这里也让人不安。
That's uncertain too.
没有这种信心的话，
Without that confidence,
成交就很难真正回暖。
transactions don't come back easily.
这里有个很重要的点。
There's an important point here.
*降息*并不总是一个好信号，
A *rate cut* is not always,
关键就在于这一点。
a positive signal.
当然，降息，
Of course, rate cuts,
对市场可能是利好的。
can be positive for the market.
但它本身，
But on their own,
并不是什么万能信号。
they are not a magic signal.
反而如果降息，
In fact, if a rate cut,
是为了应对经济衰退，
is meant to prevent an economic downturn,
人们的解读就会不一样。
people read it differently.
啊，
Oh,
是不是情况不太好了。
maybe things aren't looking good.
他们可能会这样想。
That's how they may take it.
这样一来，即使贷款条件改善了，
Then even if lending conditions improve,
也不会马上积极买房。
they don't immediately start buying aggressively.
反而会更想守住*现金*。
Instead, they try to protect their *cash*.
现在这种心理，
Right now, this kind of sentiment,
对市场的影响反而更大。
has an even bigger impact on the market.
所以就算利率下降，
That's why even if rates fall,
也不能简单认为房价会自动上涨。
you shouldn't assume,
还有一点也要看。
that home prices will automatically go up.
首尔公寓市场，
There's one more thing to watch.
并不是所有区域都会一起动。
Seoul apartments, too,
即使处在同样的利率环境下，
do not all move together.
核心地段的反应也不一样。
Even under the same rate environment,
地段好，
prime areas respond differently.
需求又扎实的地方，
Places with strong locations,
可能会撑住，甚至出现局部反弹。
and solid demand,
相反，郊区就不一样了。
can hold up or even rebound somewhat.
需求偏弱的区域，
Outlying areas are different.
反应会慢得多。
In areas with weaker demand,
为什么会出现这种差异呢？
the response is much slower.
因为现在的市场，
Why does this gap happen?
比起只看*利率一个因素*，
Because today's market,
会看更多条件。
looks at more than just *rates alone*.
供给怎么样，
It looks at supply conditions,
区域需求是否存在，
whether local demand is there,
收入条件能不能支撑，
whether incomes can support prices,
市场情绪有没有恢复，
and whether sentiment is recovering.
这些因素变得更重要了。
These factors have become more important.
归根结底，过去那套简单公式，
In the end, the simple formula from the past,
影响力已经减弱了。
has lost much of its power.
现在必须更立体地去看。
Now you have to look at the market more broadly.
那么现在，
So then,
到底该看什么呢？
what should we be watching now?
第一，
First,
要看购房意愿有没有回升。
whether buyer sentiment is recovering.
要看大家是不是结束观望，
You need to see whether people are done waiting,
真的开始行动了。
and are actually starting to move.
第二，
Second,
要看*成交量*能不能起来。
whether *transaction volume* is picking up.
比起价格，成交得先回暖，
Before prices recover, transactions have to come back first,
趋势才能延续。
for the momentum to continue.
第三，
Third,
要看各区域需求的恢复情况。
whether demand is recovering by area.
即使都在首尔，
Even within Seoul,
也要看是哪些地方先动起来，
you need to see which areas move first,
要看清其中的差别。
and watch the gap between them.
这三点都到位了，
Only when these three come together,
降息才会真正传导到房价上。
does a rate cut translate into actual price gains.
我们来总结一下。
To sum it up.
现在的市场，
Today's market,
不是一句降息就能解释清楚的。
can't be explained by a rate cut alone.
更重要的是，
What matters more,
降息之后，人们接收到什么信号，
is what kind of signal people take from it afterward.
这一点更关键。
If they feel anxious,
如果感到不安，
rates can fall and transactions still won't pick up.
就算利率下降，成交也起不来。
If they feel confident,
如果感到有信心，
that's when the market starts moving.
市场才会从那时开始动起来。
So going forward,
所以接下来，
don't just watch rates.
不要只盯着利率，
You also need to watch *sentiment*, *transaction volume*, and *local demand*,
还要把*心理*、*成交量*、*区域需求*，
together.
一起看。
The direction of home prices,
房价的走向，
depends more heavily on these three factors.
更大程度上取决于这三点。
What is your area like right now?
你所在的地区现在怎么样？
Are you seeing the impact of rates right away?
利率影响已经马上显现了吗？
Or is it still quiet?
还是说现在还很安静？
Leave a comment,
欢迎在评论区留言，
and let's take a look together.
我们一起看看。